Finding Aid for Andrew F. Wilson Papers, 1954-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Andrew F. Wilson papers 1954-1962
Wilson, Andrew F., 1918-
3.1 linear feet
90150 Aa 2
Publicist and speechwriter for George Romney, 1948-1962. Papers documenting the activities of Citizens for Michigan and its lobbying efforts in favor of a Michigan constitutional convention; include press releases, speeches, meeting minutes, financial statements and other materials relating to CFM's activities and organization; also includes speeches and statements given by George Romney from his time as President of American Motors Corporation to his run for governor of Michigan in 1962.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Andrew F. Wilson (Donor No. 7670 ) in September 1989.
The collection is open to research.
Andrew F. Wilson was born in Richmond Hill, New York in 1918. He graduated magna cum laude from the University of Notre Dame in 1939, and attended Harvard Business School for a year before becoming a newspaper reporter at the Buffalo Evening News. He entered the military in 1941, serving as an air combat intelligence officer in Europe during World War II. In 1946, Wilson returned to Buffalo and his job at the Evening News.
In 1947, Wilson joined the staff of the United Press bureau in Detroit, and the following year moved to the public relations department of the Kelvinator-Nash Company, the predecessor of the American Motors Company. He worked as public relations department executive at American Motors until 1968.
At American Motors, Wilson served as speechwriter and was in charge of publicity for George Romney, the company's president, and future governor of Michigan. In 1958, Romney founded Citizen's for Michigan (CFM), a grass-roots, non-partisan citizen's lobbying group, and Wilson followed him there as publicist and unofficial secretary of CFM. He later worked with Romney on the Coordinating Committee for a Constitutional Convention, and Romney's gubernatorial campaign, continuing to serve as Romney's speech writer. Wilson has also been involved in several other civic organizations in the Detroit area.
The Andrew F. Wilson papers document the activities of Citizens for Michigan and its grass-roots lobbying activities in support of a constitutional convention. The papers also include materials on George Romney from Wilson's files. The papers span the years of 1954-1962, however the bulk of the material is from 1959-1962. The papers are divided into four series: Citizens for Michigan; Constitutional Convention; George Romney materials; Sound Recordings; and Photographs.
Subjects:
American Motors Corporation.; Apportionment (Election law)--Michigan.; Citizens' associations--Michigan.; Citizens for Michigan.; Governors--Michigan.; Lobbying--Michigan.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Political conventions--Michigan.; Political participation--Michigan.; Politicians--Michigan.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Wilson, Andrew F., 1918-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Citizens for Michigan.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Political elections--1962.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Wilson, Andrew F., 1918-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Citizens for Michigan
  The Citizens for Michigan papers are arranged alphabetically and include: correspondence, press releases, progress reports, financial statements, minutes, speeches, printed materials, and other materials relating to CFM's organization and activities. Also included in this series is information compiled by three study committees set up by CFM to examine state needs, governmental structure, and finance. Related information on CFM during this time period can be found in the George Romney Collection, Early Series.
  - Active Organizations (Box 1)
  - Articles of incorporation and bylaws (Box 1)
  - Background information (Box 1)
  - Chapter applications (Box 1)
  - Citizen participation, papers (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Film clips (Box 1)
  - Financial statements and memos (Box 1)
  - Grant proposal to Ford Foundation 7/18/1961 (Box 1)
  - Meetings
    - 6/19/1959 (Box 1)
    - Planning Committee meeting 9/8/1959 (Box 1)
    - General membership meeting 9/21/1959 (Box 1)
    - General meeting schedule 5/21/1960 (Box 1)
    - Annual meeting workbooks 10/15/1960 (Box 1)
      (see audiotape in Box 3)
    - Committee on Taxation and Board of Directors meeting 1/21/1961 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee meeting 3/2/1961 (Box 1)
    - Annual meeting workbooks 10/28/1961 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous minutes (Box 1)
  - Membership list (Box 1)
  - Membership by regions (Box 1)
  - Newsletters (Box 1)
  - Oakes, Don, statements and memos (Box 1)
  - Organizational guide (Box 1)
  - Organizational workbook (Box 1)
  - Petition drive (Box 1)
  - Press releases
    - 11/16/1959-7/5/1960 (Box 1)
    - 7/8/1960-10/20/1961 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Printed materials (Box 1)
  - Progress reports (Box 1)
  - Seminars (Box 1)
  - Speech material (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - Professor Harvey Brazer (Box 1)
    - Professor Milton Greenberg (Box 1)
    - Professor Sherrill Cleland (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Statements (Box 1)
  - Study Committees, general (Box 1)
  - Study Committee on State Needs
    - Minutes and outlines (Box 1)
    - Reports (Box 1)
  - Study Committee on Structure
    - General (Box 1)
    - Reports (Box 1)
  - Study Committee on Finance
    - General (Box 2)
    - Reports (Box 2)
  - Wilson, Andrew 1959 file (Box 2)
- Constitutional Convention
  The Michigan Constitutional Convention (Con-Con) series is arranged alphabetically by subject and includes information on the various coordinating committees set up by CFM and other citizen's groups to lobby for the calling of a convention. The records include information on the convention, selection of delegates, and George Romney's proposals and remarks made at the convention. Romney's proposals and notes regarding the reapportionment of Michigan's congressional districts are of particular interest. Included are outsize charts used by Romney in figuring different formulas for apportionment.
  - "Address to the People" preface (Box 2)
  - Agenda and proceedings (Box 2)
  - Apportionment
    - Charts and figures (Box 2)
      (see also oversize box 4)
    - Notes (Box 2)
    - Proposals (Box 2)
    - Romney debate (Box 2)
    - Romney proposal (Box 2)
    - Wilson, Andrew, file (Box 2)
  - Background information (Box 2)
  - Committees
    - Coordinating Committee for a Constitutional Convention
      - General (Box 2)
      - Press kit 3/1961 (Box 2)
      - Statistics (Box 2)
    - Coordinating Committee for a New Constitution
      - New-Con ad campaign (Box 2)
    - Coordinating Committee for a Sound Constitution (Box 2)
  - Delegate attendance (Box 2)
  - Eisenhower visit (Box 2)
  - Governor's preparatory commission manual (Box 2)
  - Literature against (Box 2)
  - Mailing pieces and printed materials (Box 2)
  - Petitions (Box 2)
  - Proposals for reform submitted to Romney (Box 2)
  - Romney
    - Proposal and motions (Box 2)
    - Remarks 10/16/1961 (Box 2)
    - Press conference (Box 2)
  - Wilson, Andrew, personal file (Box 2)
- George Romney
  The George Romney series spans the years 1954-1962, and includes speeches, statements, and other materials from his early years at American Motors to his gubernatorial campaign in 1962. The speeches in this collection are not duplicated by the Romney speech series located in the George Romney Collection.
  - Correspondence 12/14/1960-6/22/1962 (Box 2)
  - General
    - Press conference 1954 (Box 2)
    - American Motors material 1955 (Box 2)
    - American Motors material 1956 (Box 2)
    - American Motors material 1957 (Box 3)
    - Testimony before House Judiciary Committee 2/7/1958 (Box 3)
    - Rambler Customer Sharing Program 1961 (Box 3)
    - Campaign issues 1962 (Box 3)
    - Campaign materials 1962, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Speeches
    - 1953-1959 (Box 3)
    - 1960 (Box 3)
    - 1961 (Box 3)
    - 1962 (Box 3)
    - undated (Box 3)
  - Statements
    - 9/16/1959-2/28/1961 (Box 3)
    - undated (Box 3)
- Audio-tapes
  - CFM meeting 6/15/1959, 2 reels (Box 3)
  - CFM annual meeting 10/15/1960, 3 reels (Box 3)
  - Oakland County Republican Annual Fun Day 8/26/1961, 1 reels (Box 3)
- Photographs, with some negatives
  - Citizens for Michigan board and committee members (Box 3)
  - Con-Con petition drive, fall 1960 (Box 3)
  - Press conference 02/10/1962 (Box 3)
    (Romney announcement of intention of running for governor)